AMOUZOU AGBE GUY MOREL KOSSIVI

 $Tel: +1 438 927 9764 \diamond Email: guymorel2@yahoo.fr$

Website: Guymorel.github.io

I am a near to graduate Ph.D. in economics and Statistician interested in economic modeling and applied quantitative analysis. My area of research involves labor economics, microeconometrics, development economics, and public economics. I use both experimental and non-experimental methods to address questions relating to taxation, welfare, productivity, incentive effects and human capital to help in the design and implementation of effective economic policies. I have about seven years of international experience undertaking economic and public policy research/analysis. I am bilingual, speaking and writing fluently in English and French.

EDUCATION

Laval University, Canada

Expected in Dec 2022

Ph.D. in Economics

Thesis: Three essays in Microeconometrics and Public policies with a focus on incentive effects, excess burden of taxation and post-secondary wage disparities.

Advisor Bruce Shearer; Co-Advisor Bernard Fortin

Ecole Nationale de la Statistique et de l'Analyse Economique (ENSAE), Senegal 2012-2015

M.Sc. in Economics and Statistics

University of Abomey-calavi, Benin

2010-2012

Diploma of Higher Education in Sociology-Anthropology

Ecole Nationale d'Economie Appliquée et de Management (ENEAM), Benin

2009-2012

B.Sc. in Economics and Management

POLICY EXPERIENCE

Economist-Statistician Consultant

July 2020 - Present

World Bank Group (Europe and Central Asia region), Poverty and Equity Global Practice, Washington DC

- · Global production, monitoring and analysis of harmonized indicators on poverty, shared prosperity, labor, education, energy, water and sanitation across countries and years for research and data-driven policies.
- · Research and analytical inputs for the production of World Bank documents (Poverty Assessments, Systematic Country Diagnostic, Poverty and Social Impact Analysis, Concept notes, Technical reports).
- · Analysis of poverty and inequality trends in Europe and Central Asia for research and policy making.
- · Support for statistical and data development in Europe and Central Asia for data-driven policies.
- · Statistical contribution to the COVID-19 Household Monitoring Dashboard for policy dialogue.
- · Technical support to the Europe and Central Asia region on sustainable heating issues.
- · Poverty impact analysis of rising food and energy prices in Europe and Central Asia.

World Bank Group, Social Protection and Jobs Global Practice, Washingtion DC

· Global production, monitoring and comparative analysis across countries and years of the Atlas of Social Protection Indicators of Resilience and Equity (ASPIRE) for policy and research work.

Economist-Statistician Consultant

Dec 2015 - Jun 2020

World Bank Group (Africa region), Poverty and Equity Global Practice, Washingtion DC

- · Research and analytical inputs for the production of World Bank documents (Poverty Assessments, Systematic Country Diagnostic, Poverty and Social Impact Analysis, Concept notes, Technical reports).
- · Production and cross-country analysis on poverty, labor, education, health and inequalities in Africa.
- · Assessment of water tariff reforms and poverty impacts in Niger and Mali for internal communication.
- · Analytical and technical contributions in the implementation of a social targeting program in Guinea.
- · Technical assistance on the Guinea 2018-2019 LSMS household Survey for Poverty Assessment.
- · Support for statistical and data development in Africa and data-driven policies.

RESEARCH AND TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

Jan 2018 - Present

Laval University, Quebec

- · Microeconomics II for Undergraduate (Fall 2018, Fall 2019, Fall 2022)
- · Microeconomics I for Undergraduate (Winter 2018, Winter 2019)
- · Economics for Undergraduate (Summer 2018)
- · Business economics for MBA (Fall 2021)

Research Assistant Jan - May 2020

Partnership for Economic Policy, Canada

· Research analysis on the impact of COVID-19 on poverty in the MENA countries.

Economist (Intern)

Jul 2014 - Jul 2015

International Food Policy Research Institute, Senegal

- · Estimation of Senegalese household consumption elasticities.
- · Analysis of agricultural investment strategies in Senegal.

Economist (Intern) Aug-Sep 2013

Institut National de la Statistique et de l'Analyse Economique, Benin

· Actualization of the Benin exterior trade data.

Economist (Intern) Aug-Nov 2012

Ministry of Finance and Economy, Benin

· Analysis of the socio-economic impacts of the beninese retirement reforms

RESEARCH PAPERS

- o Incentives, productivity and the excess burden of taxation: Evidence from a field experiment, 2022 (with Bruce Shearer).
- Workers' responses to piece rate reductions and increases: Evidence from a Field Experiment, 2022 (with Bruce Shearer).
- o Discontinuities in schooling and wage gap, 2022 (with Bernard Fortin).

POLICY PAPERS

- Strengthening multi-country evidence of COVID-19 on Poverty and Inequality impact and the role of Social Protection, with Tiberti et al. (2021), Partnership for Economic Policy.
- Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on poverty in MENA countries: Focus on child poverty (2021), Partnership for Economic Policy.
- o The Gambia: A Look at Agriculture, with Rose Mungai (2019), World Bank Group.
- The Republic of Niger: Building Resilience and Expanding Opportunities for All, A poverty Assessment, with Aly Sanoh et al. (2017), World Bank Group.
- Welfare and poverty impacts of cocoa price policy reform in Cote d'Ivoire, with Katayama Roy Shuji, Dabalen Andrew L. and Nssah Essama (2017), World Bank Group.
- Targeting performance of the proxy means test in Cote d'Ivoire, with Katayama Roy Shuji (2016), World Bank Group.

SCHOLARSHIPS, FELLOWHIPS AND AWARDS

• Winner of the best presentation at la Journée des étudiants du Centre de Recherche sur les	2022
risques, les enjeux économiques et les politiques publiques (CRREP)	
• Scholarship from the Quebec Interuniversity Centre for Social Statistics (QICSS)	2021
o Scolarship of Excellence from the Fonds de Recherche du Québec - Société et culture	2019-2021
• Scholarship of Excellence from the Centre de Recherche sur les risques, les enjeux	2018
économiques et les politiques publiques (CRREP)	
o Ph.D. Scholarship of Excellence from the Faculté des Sciences Sociales of Université Laval	2016-2018
 Undergraduate Scholarship of Excellence of the Government of Bénin 	2009-2012

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

Canadian Public Economic Group (CPEG) conference in 2022; la journée des étudiants du Centre de Recherche sur les risques, les enjeux économiques (CRREP) in 2022; Canadian Economics Association (CEA) Conference in 2021; les journées des étudiants du Centre de Recherche en Economie et Finance Responsables (CREFIR), du Centre de Recherche sur les risques, les enjeux économiques (CRREP) et le Centre sur le développement économique responsable (CDER) in 2019.

SOFTWARE & LANGUAGES

Statistical Software Stata, R, Matlab, SPSS, EViews, Python, SAS, GAMS, CSPro, ArcGIS

Other Software Package Office, LaTeX

Language English (Fluent), French (Native), Ewe (Fluent)

EXTRA-INFORMATION

Leadership roles Delegate of Students affiliated to the Centre de Recherche sur les risques,

les enjeux économiques et les politiques publiques (CRREP), 2019-2020;

Member of the Organization committee of the Journees d'etudiants

du CRREP held in November 2019;

Member of the ENSAE magazine writing team, 2013-2015;

General secretary of the Association of ENSAE beninese students

and interns (ASEB-ENSAE), 2014-2015.

Hobbies Traveling, Reading, Poetry, Football, Board games.

SUMMARY OF RESEARCH PAPERS

Incentives, productivity and the excess burden of taxation: Evidence from a field experiment (with Bruce Shearer), Job Market Paper, 2022

This study conducts a field experiment to analyze the disincentive effects of labor taxation on productivity (effort) and its associated social costs. Our experiment was conducted in a tree-planting firm in British Columbia where workers are hired to plant trees on given blocks and are paid on a piece rate basis. It involved two basic treatments, applying tax rates of 4 cents and 6 cents per tree with different levels of base wage. This corresponds to marginal tax rates ranging from 15% to 33% depending on the standard piece rate in place on the blocks. We applied both non-structural and structural econometric techniques on this experimental data to measure the effect of taxation on worker's effort and productivity. We show that for an average daily production of 2000 trees per worker and an initial tax rate of 15%, an increase of 10% of the tax rate will induce a decline of daily production of 28 trees per worker. This increases to 39 and 52 trees for initial tax rates of 20% and 25% respectively. Daily average excess burden on experimental observations represents 0.12 of the collected tax revenue with substantial heterogeneity across workers. We generalize our results to tax rates beyond those observed in our experiment and observe that the ratio of the excess burden to tax revenue rises disproportionately with the tax rate attaining more than 0.65 at the tax rate of 0.56 that maximizes tax revenue. Our analysis advocate for a broad-based and low tax rate system.

Workers' responses to piece-rate reductions and increases : Evidence from a Field Experiment (with Bruce Shearer), 2022

This paper analyzes workers' reactions to changes in wage rates. We use field experimental data from a tree-planting firm in British Columbia where workers are hired to plant trees on given blocks and are paid on a piece rate basis. We conduct two basic experiments to introduce exogenous variations in the worker's piece rate. The first one is a reduction of the worker's piece rate coupled with a base wage. The second one is an increase in the worker's piece rate. At the intensive margin, we measure completely piece rate effects on productivity accounting for both piece rate reductions and increases. Our study also provides a direct comparison between the impact of wage cuts and pay raises on productivity within the same framework and highlights significant asymmetries in worker's response. It establishes an empirical foundation for downward wage rigidity.

Discontinuities in post-secondary schooling and wage gap (with Bernard Fortin), 2022

The paper studies the impact of both permanent and temporary school post-secondary interruptions on wages. While most studies focus on the impact of permanent interruptions, little attention has been accorded so far to the impact of temporary school interruptions. There is however substantial empirical evidence that educational trajectories are discontinuous with episodes of temporary interruptions and re-enrollments. Using longitudinal data from two distinct cohorts of the Youth in Transition Survey in Canada, we provide empirical evidence on the impact of both permanent and temporary school interruptions. Our results are robust across these cohorts and show that there is a very slight wage penalty -less than 5%- associated to both permanent and temporary post-secondary interruption. Our study, however, shows that the wage of temporary interrupters evolves very rapidly compared to leavers and continuers. Indeed, temporary interrupters may benefit from better prospects on the labor market to tailor conveniently their skills. These results are relevant for educational policies.